Another class of algorithms in the Bandit
space which ideally I should have spent a
lot more time but we are really running out
of time in Samsung's I do not want to spend
too much time on bandits I want to get on
and talk about other topics in reinforcement
learning so there is something called
contextual bandits.
.
So what are contextual bandits one way to
think about it is to say that I am relaxing
my bandit assumption that there is no state.
I am introducing a state, right so this is
like I am taking one step from my immediate
RL problem towards the full RL problem right.
Now so what did they mediate our real problem
had it had all this Explorer exploit trade-off
stochastic right it has the are the noise
in the selections that it had the fact that
I knew about the rewards only through sampling
I do not know the true underlying reward distribution
so all of these characteristic of the reinforcement
learning problem it had.
Right so what is what is the third thing we
are adding now and adding this state dependence
right in different states I am going to have
different kinds of reward functions so what
is still missing, sequential dependence remember
I was talking to you about when cycling you
know when you might make a mistake initially
but then that is going to influence how hard
it is going to be to balance in the later
stages right so I do not have that sequential
dependence now right I so I give you a state
you give me an action right independent of
what action you selected will give you another
state.
They keep going like this so, so essentially
what you are going to do is look at an input
and then you are going to take an action right
and then you're going to move on right you
get to the wall and then you will move on
to another state so one other way of thinking
about it is to say that hey!
I am not solving one bandit problem I am solving
a set of bandit problems right and I will
tell you at every point which bandit problem
you are going to solve okay.
Here is problem three tell me what is the
option, option here is problem five tell me
what is it option like the right so one may
way to think about Saul solving this well
it's not really nice if the way I have stated
the problem ok it's pretty nice so one way
of solving this is to essentially say that
okay.
I am going to maintain suppose I have 10different
bandits i will maintain 10 different asset
of action values or 10 different sets of policies
right I am way is going to do this all independently
and I solve it okay.
So that is one way of handling it but what
if I tell you that these problems can be many
not just like a handful but i am going to
have a huge set of problems right . For example
i told you one of the success stories of reinforcement
learning was in like those new story selections
and add selections and so on so forth right
people remember that the very first class
i showed you some examples where I said Yahoo's
chose add new stories to show on the web page
by treating it as essentially they are treating
it has banded problems right.
So I have like 20 new stories when somebody
comes to the web page I will show him one
out of the 20 stories essentially like pulling
an arm and if the person clicks on it I get
a reward of 1 if they do not click on the
story I get a reward of 0 it's like a binary
bandit problem but then if i solve it as a
single banded problem it is not very interesting
right because that means that everybody who
comes to the page will get shown the same
news story or if you go back again will get
shown the same you story.
That is not going to be is not a good thing
so what you really want to do is depending
on who comes to your page right sure you want
to be able to change your choices so one way
of thinking about it is now to say that hey
i am going to group all the people coming
to my page right if somebody from Group one
comes I will use this bandit, somebody from
group 2 comes I'll use this bandit somebody
from group 3 comes I will use this bandit
right does it make sense .
And now somehow found a way of grouping them
and how do I group them.
Best well there are too many options here
so you could look at their browsing history
you could look at if they already have an
account on say Yahoo or Google or something
you can look at the data that they filled
in right.
A variety of things right so you can look
at which country they are coming from what
time of the day they are clicking from are
they are browsing from a phone, or from a
laptop so there's so much information that
each one of these internet sites gathers about
you right in fact they know more about you
then you do right.
That is not is not as stupid as you think
it is in fact there are lot of times when
people are consciously not aware of what they
are doing right but then by watching the person's
behavior they are able to form a more informed
model about you what you are trying to do
then what you yourself are doing you quite
often you are diseltarly truly doing things
right so you do not really realize what you
are what you are doing what you want anyway
so fine so you can do all kinds of things
you can group the users right.
Is that something you can do better than hmm
speech variables which variables I use include
them exactly so why, why would that help.
It will reduce the number of parameters for
each person you can define a unique set of
parameters and that's not interesting right
it's going back to solving the same problem
for you do not want them to have unique parameters
you want them to have some kind of grouping
so essentially what this will allow you to
do is it gives you greater flexibility to
figure out what kind of generalization you
want to happen over the users right
When I say fine groups right and then assign
one bandit to each group in some sense you
are making everybody in the group have the
same recommendations right the same, same
stories will be shown to them right by doing
this kind of a parameterize function so you
could be sharing some parameters with him
on four accounts right so you should be sharing
parameters with him on three other things
right so essentially there will be like a
smoother generalization across people right
so the extreme case of this would be where
everyone has a unique parameterization but.
If you make everyone you force them to be
unique then you are not doing much, much generalizations
right so you essentially want some kind of
generalization to happen so that will kind
of fallout from doing this in a parameterization
fashion right.
So there are many ways so contractual bandits
is just a problem setting there are many ways
of solving it one of them is to do this kind
of parameterization of the value depending
on, the state as well as the action.
So what I mean by the action here the action
can have parameters so what do I mean by that
let go back to the new story case right, so
I can think of it as new story one I can also
think of it as political article, from India
right about the central whatever so I mean
I can I can think of some kind of attributes
that describe the new story as well right
so these are attributes that describe my arm
they are not describing my states.
They are describing my arm so in this case
state or the people who are coming to the
page and arms are the new stories right so
I could have attributes that describe both
the new stories on the arms I am sorry and
the users and i can use all of these satellites
to define my value function so I can have
a parameterization that depends on both the
actions and the state it apart from that I
could have additional parameterizations like,
like this for defining my value functions
and my and my policy’s.
.
Whatever alright so
and people talk about parameterized bandits
typically they talk about parameter zing the
value functions okay not necessarily the policy
gradient kind of things even though this is
also a form of parameterized bandits.
When typically when people talk about parameterized
bandits in the contextual bandit can kiss
they are talking about parameter zing the
value functions okay.
And just, just point out these are very close
and sometimes they are used interchangeably
like parameterized bandits or linear bandits.
Where the, the function value function is
assumed to be linear in the set of parameters
that you have right so that is linear band
it's right and contextual bandits are often
use interchangeably but there is a certain
difference contextual bandits is a problem
setting while linear bandits is a specific
way of solving that problem.
So contractual bandage is essentially like
I said there are many ways in which you can
solve it right you can just replicate the
bandits you can do group and then solve we
do not really have to assume some kind of
parameterization but that's it so this again
very, very popular now in fact most deployments
of bandits right use this kind of parameterized
contextual bandits so for example the one
of the most popular deployments of UCB.
Right only UCB has become the most popular
bandit algorithm right but the most popular
deployment of UCB we find is called Lin UCB
which is UCB with a linear parameterization
assume for the value functions so I will assume
some set of parameters I will assume my Q
of a right that is what I am estimating my
cue of EA is some function of these parameters
and that function is linear in the parameters
right.
So that's essentially what Lane you see we
would do right and then you have to have some
mechanism by which you determine what the
upper confidence bounds are right.
So, it's a slightly different update rule
then what we do for UCB but it is more or
less the, the same principle right so I will
be doing something like this should be something
like this.
.
So ?1 ?2 ?3 will be my parameters I assume
for the representation.
So fine so I will stop here there will be
the end of bandits.
So next class I will start with chapter 3
in the book so if you want to read ahead please
do so.